Guide to the John T. Ridge Collection AIA.068
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John T. Ridge Collection
1735-2002
1860-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ridge, John T.
AIA.068
10.25 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 3 record cartons, 3 oversize flat boxes, 3 media boxes, 12 custom boxes, and 5 oversize folders
John T. Ridge is a founding member and current president of the New York Irish History Roundtable. The son of Irish immigrants, Ridge is a Brooklyn-based historian whose work focuses on the influence of social events and organizations such as the Ancient Order of Hibernians, St. Patrick’s Day parades, and Gaelic language clubs, with particular emphasis on the greater New York City area. Materials in this collection include books, booklets, buttons, ribbons, periodicals, ledgers, postcards, broadsides, photographs, advertisements, correspondence, event programs, sheet music, and newspaper and magazine clippings related to Irish and Irish American history in the late 19th- and early 20th-centuries. The majority of the collection documents fraternal and social Irish American organizations in the New York area, as well as numerous nationalist and republican organizations or initiatives.
Arrangement
Files are arranged into two series, thereunder alphabetically:
Series I. Social Organizations and Early Irish America
Series II. Patrick Mullin Irish People Materials
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Biographical Note
John T. Ridge is a founding member and current president of the New York Irish History Roundtable. The son of Irish immigrants, Ridge is a Brooklyn-based historian whose work focuses on the influence of social events and organizations such as the Ancient Order of Hibernians, St. Patrick’s Day parades, and Gaelic language clubs, with particular emphasis on the greater New York City area. He has also led guided tours of immigration facilities and area cemeteries, and given lectures on various aspects of Irish and Irish American history. In addition to numerous essays and journal articles, Ridge also wrote the books The Flatbush Irish, Celebrating 250 Years of the New York City St. Patrick’s Day Parade, Erin’s Sons in America: The Ancient Order of Hibernians, and Sligo in New York: The Irish From County Sligo, 1849-1991.
Related Archival Materials
Collection on the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AIA 046)
Irish Republicanism Collection (AIA 022)
Scope and Contents Note
This is an intentionally assembled collection of materials related to Irish and Irish American history in the late 19th- and early 20th-centuries. Materials include books, booklets, buttons, ribbons, periodicals, ledgers, postcards, broadsides, photographs, advertisements, correspondence, event programs, sheet music, and newspaper and magazine clippings. The collection documents various fraternal and social Irish American organizations, with particular emphasis on the Ancient Order of Hibernians divisions located in the greater New York City area, including photographs, convention proceedings, and ledger books. Other materials document American expressions of Irish nationalism and republicanism, including those of the American Commission on Irish Independence, the American League for an Undivided Ireland, the Friends of Irish Freedom, Irish Northern Aid, and the Loyal National Repeal Association. Of note is an issue of John Mitchel's radical nationalist New York newspaper, The Citizen. While the majority of the collection is political in scope, some folders contain advertisements, documents, or photographs of Irish actors, commercial goods, or theatrical performances.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Ridge, 2012. The accession number associated with this gift is 2013.007.
Ireland -- History -- 20th century.; Ireland -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Social life and customs.; Northern Ireland -- History -- 1969-1994.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Periodicals.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activities.; Ancient Order of Hibernians
- Series I: Social Organizations and Early Irish America, 1735-2002; 1860-1964; 5.25 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 2 and a half record cartons, 3 media boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 12 custom boxes, and 5 oversize folders.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials documenting participation in Irish American organizations, cultural expressions of Irish nationalism and republicanism, and other material collected by John T. Ridge. Materials in this series date from the mid-18th century to 2000, with the bulk of the materials dating from the late 19th century to the 1970s. The bulk of this series documents activities of the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH) divisions located in the greater New York City area as well as the national organization. AOH materials include photographs, convention proceedings, ledger books, and Hibernian Monthly Magazine. Other organizations represented include the County Cavan Society, County Tyrone Society, Friends of Irish Freedom, Irish Northern Aid, and the Loyal National Repeal Association. Other materials include day books of fire departments in New York City, biographies and histories relating to Irish history, Irish language grammar books, John Mitchel’s radical Irish nationalist newspaper, The Citizen, sheet music, ephemera, correspondence, event programs, and newspaper and magazine clippings.
  - "The 69th (Irish) Regiment Emarking In the "James Adger" For the War, April 23, 1961," Harper's, May 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advertisement: Irish Beauty, Shamrock Oranges, circa 1937 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Advertisement: McQuade's Mountain Dew Whisky, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advertisement: Schultz's Irish Soap, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Commission on Irish Independence, May 21, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American League for an Undivided Ireland, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: 25th Anniversary and 50th Anniversary of the Manchester Martyrs, 1917, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: 40th Annual Kings County Communion Breakfast; Hotel St. George, Mar 4, 1962 (Flat-file 7, Drawer 14, Folder 3)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: 43rd Biennial Convention Proceedings, 1902 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: 61st Biennial Convention Dinner Dance, St. James Cathedral; Brooklyn, NY, Aug 15, 1939 (Flat-file 7, Drawer 15, Folder 1)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: 61st Biennial Convention Dinner Dance, Communion Breakfast, St. Brigid Dinner (Ladies' Auxiliary); United Irish Societies of Brooklyn and Long Island Dinner Dance for John O'Hagen Panoramas, 1939-1941 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: 77th Biennial National Convention Proceedings, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Annual Luncheon, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Cash Book, 1953-2000 (Box 15)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Communion Breakfast Panoramas, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Communion Breakfasts, Division 33 Dinner, and Dinner Dance for William O'Dwyer Panoramas, 1944-1946 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Communion Breakfasts and Dinner Dance Panoramas, 1942-1943 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Communion Breakfasts and Dinner Dance Panoramas, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Communion Breakfasts and Dinner Dance Panoramas, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Communion Breakfasts and Dinner Dance Panoramas, 1951-1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Communion Breakfasts, St. Brigid Banquet; Testimonial Dinners for John O'Hagen and William F. Zundel, 1934-1939 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Communion Breakfasts Panoramas, 1953-1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Division 9 Finance Books (9th Ward/Crown Heights, Brooklyn), 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Division 35 (Flatbush, Brooklyn) Group Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Division 35 Minute Books, 1957-1995 (Box 17, Box 21)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Division 35 Notebook, 1950s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Kings County Convention By-laws, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Kings County Ledger, 1937-1973 (Box 12)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Ladies' Auxiliary of New York State: 76th Biennial Convention, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Ladies' Auxiliary of New York State: 77th Biennial Convention, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Ladies' Auxiliary of New York State: 78th Biennial Convention, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 53rd National Convention Proceedings, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 54th National Convention Proceedings, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 55th National Convention Proceedings, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 58th National Convention Proceedings, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 60th National Convention Proceedings, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 61st National Convention Proceedings, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 62nd National Convention Proceedings, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11, Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 63rd National Convention Proceedings, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 65th National Convention Proceedings, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 66th National Convention Proceedings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 67th National Convention Official Call, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 69th National Convention Panorama, Aug 5, 1958 (Flat-file 7, Drawer 14, Folder 2)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 69th National Convention Proceedings, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: National Convention: 74th National Convention, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: New York State Board: 75th Biennial Convention, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: New York State Board: State Convention, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Passwords and Quiz, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Ribbons, Badges, and Buttons, 1890-1975 (Box 3-4)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Objects are extremely fragile and cannot be removed from their housing without approval and assistance from the Preservation Department.
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Ritual Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings, 1897 (Box 22)
  - Artwork: Robert Emmet, "Ireland's Illustrious Sons," Ancient Order of Hibernians Ladies Auxiliary, undated (Flat-file 7, Drawer H, Folder 3)
  - Assorted correspondence and newsletters, 1975-2002 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Cassidy, Charles W., 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Barry and Fay's Comedy Co.: "Muldoon's Picnic", Dec 19, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Broadsides, John Devoy, Longstrike and Scenes in the Life of Robert Emmet, Shaughran, 1867, 1874, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Catholic Temperance Abstinence Union of America, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ċeallaċáin, Máire Ní: Irish at Home, 1922 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Cigar Labels, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Citizen, 1854 (Box 6, Folder 3, Box 14)
  - Clippings, 1865, 1893, 1940, undated (Box AIAOS002, Folder 7)
  - Comhaltas Ceoltoiri Eireann: Annual U.S. Concert Tour of All-Ireland Champions, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Corcoran, Col. Michael, circa 1863 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - County Cavan Society, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - County Tyrone Society, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "The Escape of Stevens" Broadside, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Fate of the Irish Republic," The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator, circa 1878-1951 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Fenian Bond, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Fire Department Day Books, 1878, 1884, 1889, 1892-1893 (Box 13, Box 16, Box 18, Box 19)
  - The Flatbush Hibernian, 1972-1982 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom: General, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom: Constitution, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom: "The Escape from Mountjoy and Other Prison Experiences of an irish Volunteer, Padraic Fleming", circa 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom: Financial Secretary's Files, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom: Membership Applications, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom: Membership Renewals and New Membership Cards, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Frontispiece Featuring New York City Mayor John T. Hoffman, after 1866 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ginnell, Laurence: The Irish Republic. Why?, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - "Greetings to a Great Fighter from Thomas A. Lenehan", 1943 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Hartley, Thomas W.: The Celebrated Speech of General Thomas F. Burke, 1871 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - The Hibernian Monthly Magazine, 1895 November-1896 December (Box 11, Folder 3-11)
  - House Documents: The Irish Question Hearing, 1918-1919 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "In Memory of Charles O'Connor", Dec 8, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Irish American Democratic Union, circa 1890-1895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Irish Northern Aid (Brooklyn), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Irish Pictorial, 1860 (Box 20)
  - Irish Race Fund, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator, 1911 (Flat-file 7, Drawer H, Folder 1)
  - The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator, Jun 3, 1911 (Flat-file 7, Drawer H, Folder 2)
  - Joseph Murphy's Three Great Irish Plays, late 1800s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Joyce, P.W.: A Grammar of the Irish Language for the Use of Schools, 1879 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Letters to John From Ed, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Loyal National Repeal Association, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Loyal Orange Lodge, Dec 10, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - MacManus, Seumas: Ireland's Case, 2nd Edition, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - McGee, Thomas D'Arcy: A History of the Irish Settlers in North America: From the Earliest Period to the Census of 1850, 1851 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Memorial Card: Seaun Allis Treacy, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Millard, Dr. S.L. (Boston), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - New York County Service Bounty, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - O'Brien, Michael J.: The McCarthys in Early American History, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - O'Brien, Michael J.: Timothy Murphy: Hero of the American Revolution, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "O'Donovan Rossa's Shooting Gallery," Puck, Jan 21, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - O'Duffy, R.J.: Historic Graves in Glasnevin Cemetery, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Olcott, Chauncey, circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - O'Mahony, John, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Postcards, undated (Box 5, Box 9, Folder 21)
  - St. Patrick's Cathedral, 1862-1866 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - St. Patrick's Cathedral Cornerstone Laying, The Emerald, 1868 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Saint Patrick's Society of Kings County (Brooklyn) Minute Book, circa 1850 (Box 8)
  - Second Boer War, circa 1899-1902 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sheehy, Rev. D.J.: Notes on the Irish-Canadian Pilgrimage and Addresses, 1892 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Sheet Music, 1844, 1863, 1920, undated (Box AIAOS002, Folder 8)
  - Sheet Music: "Aileen Mavourneen", circa 1860 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Sheet Music: "The Bells of St. Patrick's Cathedral", after 1951 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Sheet Music: "The Irishman's Shanty", after 1859 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Sheet Music: "Since Home Rule's Come to Ireland", 1914 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Smith, Charles: Smith's History of Waterford, 1735 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Spalding, J.L.: The Religious Mission of the Irish People and Catholic Colonization, 1880 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Spalding, J.L.: The Religious Mission of the Irish People and Catholic Colonization, 3rd Edition, 1880 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Stang, Rev. William: Germany's Debt to Ireland, 1889 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Stephens, James: Harper's, Jun 2, 1866 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "Sweet Dreams" Cartoon in Judge, circa 1881-1947 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Tailteann Games, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Theater Programs: "The Little Irish Girl," "The Voice of McConnell", circa 1918-1926 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Truth Teller, 1830 (Box 23)
  - United Irish Counties Association (UICA) Feis Card, Jun 13, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - United Irishmen Philadelphia Records, 1792-1799 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Wearing of the Green," Arrah Na Pogue, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series II: Patrick Mullin Irish People Materials, 1984-1989; 0.5 Linear Feet in one half of a record carton.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains materials created or collected by Patrick Mullin during his time working with the Irish People newspaper. The New York-based publication was a weekly, volunteer-run paper that described itself as the "Voice of Irish Republicanism in America." It provided coverage and analysis of events in Ireland and America concerning conflict in Northern Ireland and more general British involvement in Ireland. In addition to meeting minutes, this series contains many of the publication's financial records, reflecting its relationship with Noraid (Irish Northern Aid) and other politically involved organizations.
  - Irish American Defense Fund, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Irish American Defense Fund and Irish People Audit, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Irish People: Financial Records, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 28-32)
  - Irish People: Lease, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Irish People: Meeting Minutes, Mar 1987 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Irish People: Tax Return, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Kearney, Oliver. "Playing for Time", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Sinn Fein Report on Irish American Organizations and Political Involvement, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)